Guide to the American College for Girls records,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
American College for Girls Records,
1880s-1979.
American College for Girls (Istanbul, Turkey)
27 linear ft. (58 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library New York, NY. 10027
6799283
These records contain information related to the formation of the American College for Girls. They document the founders' attempts to define the mission of a Christian women's college within the Ottoman Empire.
Historical Note
The American College for Girls was an outgrowth of an educational experiment called The Home School founded in 1871 in Istanbul by the Woman's Board of Missions and a group of women educators from Boston. Under the leadership of May Mills Patrick, and with the support of Sarah L. Bowker, Caroline Borden and other Boston women, the school was granted an act of incorporation as an educational institution in 1890 by the Commonwealth of Massachusetts. The Home School had been gradually adding post-high school course work over the years and in June 1891 conferred Bachelor of Arts degrees on its first seven graduates. As in the case of Robert College, ACG enrolled the Christian minorities within the Ottoman Empire. The first Turkish women attended surreptitiously, but more openly and in increasing numbers following the Young Turk uprising of 1908.
The American College for Girls was an outgrowth of an educational experiment called The Home School founded in 1871 in Istanbul by the Woman's Board of Missions* and a group of women educators from Boston. Under the leadership of May Mills Patrick, and with the I support of Sarah L. Bowker, Caroline Borden and other Boston women, the school was granted an act of incorporation as an educational institution in 1890 by the Commonwealth of Massachusetts. The Home School had been gradually adding post-high school course work over the years and in June 1891 conferred Bachelor of Arts degrees on its first seven graduates. As in the case of Robert College, ACG enrolled the Christian minorities within the Ottoman Empire. The first Turkish women attended surreptitiously, but more openly and in increasing numbers following the Young Turk uprising of 1908.
The process of recruiting faculty members was a difficult one and some instructors pursued graduate work while they taught. In December 1905 a disastrous fire destroyed Barton Hall, the main instructional building, but fortunately no lives were lost. In the next few years Dr. Patrick increased her efforts to expand the college's facilities and by 1914 property had been purchased at Arnavutköy and four new buildings constructed. A fifth, Bingham Hall, was added in 1924. In the meantime the college had secured a second charter from the Massachusetts legislature in 1908 allowing it to develop independently from the restrictions of the Woman's Board of Missions.
The dedication of the new campus was followed in the same year by the outbreak of World War I. Remarkably, the college survived the privations of wartime Istanbul and the Turkish government permitted it to function even after the U.S. declared war on Turkey's allies, the Central Powers. Although some students represented nationalities at war with each other they continued to pursue their education side by side during the four years of the conflict.
One of Dr. Patrick's strongest convictions was that medical education be available to women. In 1920 a medical department was opened at ACG together with the founding of The American Hospital (subsequently known as the Admiral Bristol Hospital). By 1924, however, the trustees of the college concluded that they could not continue to fund the medical department. Shortly afterward the Turkish government decided to limit such professional training to its own educational institutions.
In 1924 Dr. Patrick retired and was succeeded by Kathryn Newell Adams, who had headed the English Department since 1920. She served until 1931.
Prior to the appointment of Paul Monroe in 1932 as the president of both Robert College and the American College for Girls, the two institutions had begun sharing instructors for certain elective classes. The stringencies imposed by the depression led to further consolidation.
When ill health compelled the retirement of Dr. Monroe in 1935, he was succeeded as head of the two institutions by Dr. Walter Livingston Wright, Jr., an Ottoman scholar whose extensive knowledge of the Near East served the colleges well during an era of profound change in Turkey. President Wright faced the continuous task of maintaining academic standards in the face of financial stringency. The curriculum underwent revision as the college strove to adapt to the needs of a nation undergoing modernization.
As Europe's crises of the late 1930s brought war in 1939, it became increasingly difficult to attract qualified teachers. Moreover, when the U.S. became involved in 1941, President Wright was called to Washington to serve as an advisor on Near Eastern affairs. Dean Harold L. Scott, who had served Robert College in several capacities since 1911, guided the institutions through most of the war years acting as president. In 1944 Floyd Henson Black was appointed president of the college. His first teaching position had been as a tutor at Robert College in 1911. In 1914 he had returned to the United States and after completing his doctorate at Harvard he it returned in 1919 to teach Latin. In 1926 he was appointed president of the American College in Sofia where he served for the next eighteen years. By 1944, however, the war forced the closing of the college in Sofia and Floyd Black returned, this time to a combined Robert College and American College for Girls, to lead it into the postwar years. By the war's end the college was highly respected in Turkey and there was no difficulty attracting students. The problems centered on a shortage of faculty and the college's aging physical facilities. Financial constraints and an overburdened faculty threatened an erosion of academic standards, even while extracurricular activities, drama, and athletics flourished. The college found itself at a crossroads and with the impending retirement of Dr. Black in 1955, the faculty sought to re-evaluate the academic needs of the institution while the trustees undertook to seek new sources of funding.
In 1955 Dr. Duncan Ballantine, President of Reed College, was appointed by a joint presidential search committee composed of RC and ACG trustees. His mandate was to revitalize the academic programs at the college. After a year-long study sweeping changes were made. The orta, which trained eleven to fourteen-year-old youngsters, was phased out. The four-year lise was made comparable to the three-year Turkish lise and designated Robert Academy. The collegiate division was granted permission by the Turkish Government to award Bachelor of Arts and Bachelor of Science degrees as well as Masters degrees in both fields. The college program was reorganized into three departments, the Engineering School, the School of Business Administration, and the School of Science and Foreign Languages. All three departments were to be coeducational.
Timeline:
1863 - Robert College founded by Hamlin and Robert.
1871 - American College for Girls (originally known as The Home School) founded in Gedikpaşa.
1874 - American College for Girls moved to Üsküdar.
1912 - Engineering school opened at Robert College (with first civil engineering program in Turkey).
1914 - American College for Girls moved to Arnavutköy campus.
1932 - Administration of RC and ACG united under leadership of a single president.
1958 - Three new schools added to the degree-granting Yüksek (Higher Education) Division of Robert College. Boards of Trustees and endowment funds of both Colleges merged under the name of the Trustees of Robert College of Istanbul.
1971 - Robert College Yüksek transferred to the Turkish Government and now carries on the Robert academic tradition as Boğaziçi University. Robert Academy and ACG combined physically on the Arnavutköy campus as a co- educational six-year preparatory school.
Scope and Content
The records of Robert College are organized into fourteen series, while those of the American College for Girls comprise eight series. In addition, there is a vital documents series, a substantial collection of photographs, and a sizable body of records that include both colleges.
The collection also contains personal papers of some of the leading figures in the history of each institution, notably Cyrus Hamlin, George Washburn, Christopher Robert, Caleb F. Gates, Mary Mills Patrick and Caroline Borden. Cyrus Hamlin's earliest papers date from the 1830s, while the correspondence of the correspondence Caleb Gates and Mary Patrick extends into their retirement years as they continued to remain in close touch with their colleagues and former students.
The earliest records of ACG date from 1890, the year of its founding with a charter from the Commonwealth of Massachusetts. The records are not as complete for the early years as for the later ones. Nevertheless, they document the pioneering role of ACG in opening higher education to women in the Near East and thereby enrich our understanding of the dramatic changes in the changes in the status of women during the twentieth century.
The collection contains a large proportion of college officials in Istanbul and the Office York. The vital role played by the trustees and material support to both colleges is well documented. Throughout the correspondence that concerns the operations of the colleges there can be found many commentaries on events in Turkey and the outlying regions of the Ottoman Empire. Moreover, the administrators of both institutions reported on their travels in Europe and the Near East. They wrote about Turkey and conditions during the Russo-Turkish conflict and both World Wars. Finally, they followed with great interest the modernization in Turkey and sought to adapt their own institutions to the far-reaching changes in Turkish society. Thus, while theses records contain the history of two American colleges, they are also significant sources for the study of modern Turkey. Accordingly, extensive descriptions of each record series are provided.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in 11 series and 1 addition:
Series I: Records of the Trustees
Subseries I.1: Woman's Board of Missions
Subseries I.2: Report and Minutes
Subseries I.3: General Correspondence
Subseries I.4: Papers of Caroline Borden
Subseries I.5: Records Relating to Land Acquisition
Subseries I.6: The Committee on Instruction, 1905-1924
Subseries I.7: The Committee on Finance, 1907-1933
Subseries I.8: The Building Committee, 1908-1921
Subseries I.9: The Committee on Medical Education
Subseries I.10: General
Series II: Office of the President
Subseries II.1: Annual Reports
Subseries II.2: Correspondence
Series III: Office of the Dean
Series IV: Office of the Secretary and Bursar
Series V: Records of the Faculty
Series VI: Office of the Trustees, New York
Series VII: Financial Records, 1899-1946
Series VIII: Publicity, Official Events and Historical
Series IX: Minutes
Series X: Photographs
Series XI: Microfilms
Additional I
Subjects
American College for Girls (Istanbul, Turkey); Robert College (Istanbul, Turkey); Patrick, Mary Mills, 1850-1940.; Istanbul (Turkey); Turkey--Description and travel.; Turkey--History--1878-1909.; Education--Turkey.; Universities and colleges--Turkey--Istanbul--History--19th century.; Universities and colleges--Turkey--Istanbul--History--20th century.; Women--Education--Turkey.; Women--Turkey.; Women missionaries--Turkey.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
Robert College Purchase, 2006.
Finding aid in repository; folder level control.
- Series 1: Records of the Trustees
  - Subseries I.1: Woman's Board of Missions
    The bulk of the ACG records are those of the trustees. These include the work of their most important committees. The early records beginning in 1890 reflect the sponsorship of the college by the Woman's Board of Missions. Mary Mills Patrick, president, Florence Fensham, dean, and others provide accounts to the board of the work of the college. In the main, these reflect the day-to-day decisions necessary to develop a fledgling institution under less than ideal conditions. Important subjects covered in the early years are Patrick's efforts to secure property rights for a permanent campus, and an imperial Irade to formalize approval of the college by the Sultan. Issuance was announced in April 1895.
    As early as 1893, ACG's advisory board raised the issue of separating the college from the Woman's Board of Missions so that it would stand on its own. Those who favored this believed that the college would then have broader appeal when it asked for contributions from denominations other than the Congregationalist-sponsored Woman's Board of Missions.
    In addition to the ever-present matters of finances and supplies, a recurrent subject is the recruitment of faculty. Given the distance and slow means of communication between the United States and Turkey, there was necessarily much discussion of the qualifications of prospective teachers and the terms of their contracts.
    - Bound Volume: General correspondence to President Mary Mills Patrick and Dean Florence Fensham from secretaries E. Harriet Stanwood and Abbie Child, 1900-1905 (Box 1)
    - Bound Volume: General correspondence written by Sarah L. Day, treasurer, and Stanwood, secretary. 1905-1908 (Box 1)
    - Correspondence Fensham/Child 1890 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - General correspondence to Child, Ellen Carruth, and Mrs. Judson Smith, 1890-1892 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Resignation of Caroline Borden as Secretary of the Corporation, 1893 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - General correspondence to Child, 1894-1895 (Box 2, Folder 4-5)
    - Correspondence to Child and Smith from Patrick and others, 1893;1895 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Reports to Child and Stanwood from Patrick, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - General correspondence to Stanwood, 1896 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence to Child, Smith from Patrick and others, 1897 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Reports to Child from Patrick, 1898-1900 (Box 2, Folder 10-11)
    - General correspondence to Child, Stanwood and Smith, 1899-1900 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - General correspondence to trustees (most relates to separation of ACG from the Board of Missions and establishment of a medical department), 1901 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - General correspondence to Child and Stanwood from Patrick and others, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Reports to Stanwood and Smith from Patrick and Fensham, 1903 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - General correspondence to trustees re Fensham's resignation, 1904 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Reports to Stanwood from Patrick (also includes letter from Robert Thomson to Stanwood re religious status of ACG), 1904 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - General correspondence to Stanwood (includes resignation 1905 from Day) (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Reports to Stanwood from Patrick 1905 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - General correspondence, Woman's Board of Missions 1906 (Box 2, Folder 19a)
    - Reports to Stanwood from Patrick 1906 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - General correspondence to Stanwood 1906 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Reports to Stanwood from Patrick (much of the correspondence relates to possible purchase of the Arnavutköy property. Also see land series.), 1906 (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Correspondence to Stanwood from Roxana Vivian, acting president, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Subseries I.2: Report and Minutes
    Minutes and reports of ACG's Board of Trustees* and its various committees, such as Finance, Nominations, Instruction, and Buildings and Grounds. There are in addition president's and treasurer's reports.
    - Miscellaneous organizational notes re trustees and faculty, 1900s (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Minutes of the first meeting of the Advisory Committee in New York, 1904-1906 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - List of original trustees, 1907 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Secretary's report on the organization of trustees, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - First Annual Report of the secretary of the trustees, 1908 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Tribute to the memory of Professor Borden P. Bowne, president of the board, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Acknowledgement of John D. Rockefeller's gift, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Minutes of trustees' meetings [A complete set of trustees minutes is in the Vital Documents Series], 1912 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Minutes of trustees' meetings, 1915-1920 (Box 3, Folder 9-12)
    - Reports and minutes of trustees' meetings kept by Walter B. Walker (bound volume), 1910-1922 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - "Information in Regard to ACG…Including Trustees, 1916-. Property, Attendance, Curriculum, Faculty and its Training, the Financing of the College, and Future Plans", 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence, reports, minutes, 1910­1919 (Box 3, Folder 15-16)
    - Committee meetings, minutes, miscellaneous, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Miscellaneous (includes unidentified letters) 1915, 1919 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Subseries I.3: General Correspondence
    The general correspondence files contain many letters from Mary Mills Patrick that are richly detailed, not only for their description of college activities, but also for the information they convey about Istanbul in the early 20th century.
    - Reports to Samuel Darling from Patrick, 1908-1909 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Reports to Darling from Vivian, 1908-1909 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Reports to Darling from Patrick and general correspondence, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Reports to Darling from Patrick and Eleanor Burns, 1911 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Reports to Darling from Patrick, 1912-1914 (Box 4, Folder 5-7)
    - General correspondence to Darling, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence to Charles Crane from Patrick, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence to Darling from Patrick, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - General correspondence to Darling, 1920 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence to Crane from Patrick, 1921-1924 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Correspondence to Crane from Kathryn Adams, 1923-1925 (Box 4, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence to Grace Dodge from Patrick; includes 1912-1913 letters re medical department and increasing tuition, 1912-1913 (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence to Dodge from Patrick, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 15)
    - Grace Dodge; obituary and correspondence re memorial service, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    - General correspondence to Dodge, 1914-1915 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence to William Adams Brown, chairman of Search 1915 Committee. Contains description of Adams's qualifications to succeed Patrick, 1915 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Clippings on Bowne, 1906 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Copy of Henry Morgenthau's letter to Mrs. Russell Sage, 1914 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - General correspondence to trustees, 1915-1923 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Report to trustees on trip to Turkey and visit to ACG by Albert B. Hart, [undated] (Box 4, Folder 22)
    - Report by Hart on visit to ACG [made between 1900 and 1914], [undated] (Box 4, Folder 23)
    - Reports on visits to various colleges in the Near East [Staub?], 1920s (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Report on visit to Turkey by Philip Brown titled, "American Educational Institutions in Turkey", 1933 (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - "Laws for Private Schools," document issued by the Turkish Government, 1922 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Subseries I.4: Papers of Caroline Borden
    Caroline Borden was one of the most active of the trustees and her papers fill four boxes documenting her activities on behalf of the college. Her warm friendship with Mary Mills Patrick is reflected in their correspondence, and Patrick writes in considerable detail about life at the college with a sprinkling of comments on the political climate in Istanbul. Many administrative issues are discussed, principally the proposed moving of the campus from Uskudar to Arnavutköy.
    Borden's own letters demonstrate her active role in the campaign to secure an act of incorporation for ACG from the Massachusetts legislature. In later years she worked to raise funds for the new campus and was supportive of the college in a variety of ways. Caroline Borden was also interested in preserving the history of ACG. Her papers contain notes and chronologies for her manuscript history of the college which is a separately bound volume in the archives.
    - Correspondence to Borden from Patrick, 1890-1906 (Box 5, Folder 1-9)
    - Correspondence to Borden from Patrick and Vivian, 1907-1910 (Box 5, Folder 10-12)
    - Correspondence to Borden from Patrick, 1911-1912 (Box 5, Folder 13-18)
    - Correspondence to Borden from Patrick, 1913-1920 (Box 6, Folder 19-24)
    - General correspondence to Borden, 1890-1907 (Box 6, Folder 25-31)
    - General correspondence to Borden (includes letters from Vivian), 1908 (Box 6, Folder 32)
    - General correspondence to Borden, 1909-1921 (Box 6, Folder 33-38)
    - Correspondence to Borden from Susan Olmstead, 1895-1921 (Box 7, Folder 39-43)
    - Correspondence to Borden from Ida Prime, 1902-1921 (Box 7, Folder 44-50)
    - Correspondence to Borden from William Peet, 1898-1920 (Box 7, Folder 51-52)
    - Correspondence to Borden from Morgenthau, 1914-1916 (Box 7, Folder 53)
    - Copies of correspondence; general, 1905-1914 (Box 7, Folder 54-57)
    - Correspondence to Borden from Dodge, 1908-1915 (Box 7, Folder 57a)
    - Copies of correspondence; general, 1915-1920 (Box 8, Folder 58-60)
    - Copies of Borden's correspondence to Patrick, 1908-1917 (Box 8, Folder 61)
    - Copies of Borden's correspondence to George Plimpton, 1909-1921 (Box 8, Folder 62)
    - Copies of Borden's correspondence to Samuel Dutton and Talcott Williams, 1901-1921 (Box 8, Folder 63)
    - Copies of Borden's correspondence to Walter Walker 1914-1920 (Box 8, Folder 64)
    - Copies of Borden's correspondence to Edward Haskell, 1920 (Box 8, Folder 65)
    - Borden's summary notes of important events; many notes taken from the record book of Darling, secretary, 1908-1913 (Box 8, Folder 66)
    - Extracts from letters re buildings on campus, 1908 (Box 8, Folder 67)
    - Borden's notes for history of ACG, 1875-1917 (Box 8, Folder 68)
    - Borden's notes; chronological history, 1907-1913 (Box 8, Folder 69)
    - Background information; origin and sketch of ACG prepared by Borden, 1904 (Box 8, Folder 70)
    - Paper by Borden on negotiations for Arnavutköy property. Also, copy of letter from Sir Edwin Pears to U.S. Minister Oscar Straus, 1908 (Box 8, Folder 71)
    - Copies of letters re acquisition of Arnavutköy property, 1908-1910 (Box 8, Folder 72)
    - Scrapbook containing clippings, invitations, letters (Appears to belong to Caroline Border), 1880s-ca.1907 Fragile (Box 8a)
  - Subseries I.5: Records Relating to Land Acquisition
    The acquisition of property for a foreign school was an intricate and difficult process under the Ottoman Empire. In December 1905 a fire completely destroyed Barton Hall. The disaster set in motion an effort to establish a new and larger campus. The process involved attempts to enlist the aid of the U.S. Government, which included a meeting between President Theodore Roosevelt and an American delegation from ACG. Ultimately the Arnavutköy property was purchased and later the Deli Bedros property. The central figure in these efforts was William W. Peet, a trustee of ACG (Boxes 9-10).
    - Notes and outline of events on property acquisition, "Constantinople Controversy", 1907-1908 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Peet's correspondence re land acquisition, 1907-1908 (Box 9, Folder 2-5)